Malay SINGH

5 Dover Crescent, Dover Court, #04-18, Singapore, 130005.

Mob: +65-8425-3120.

E-mail: malay.1989@gmail.com,

Websites: http://malaysinghnus.github.io; ResearchGate;LinkedIn; Google Scholar.

ORCID: 0000-0002-2219-8287

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My current research focuses on applications of image processing, computer vision, machine learning, pattern recognition and mathematical modeling in biological and biomedical image analysis and informatics.

I have been developing algorithms for histological tissue images analysis. My research includes developing automatic feature extraction and classification methods to solve object detection, object classification and image segmentation problems in histopathological tissue images.

EDUCATION

Jan 2013 - Dec 2017 Ph.D. in Computer Science,

School of Computing, National University of Singapore. Singapore.

Thesis: Automated Image Based Tools For Digital Pathology.

Research Area: Digital Pathology, Computer Vision, Machine Learning. Supervisors: Dr. Hwee Kuan LEE and Prof. Wing-Kin SUNG, Ken.

Jul 2008 - Jun 2012 B.Tech. in Information Technology (Hons.),

Indian Institute of Information Technology Allahabad. Prayagraj, India.

Thesis: Speech Retrieval.

Research Area: Speech Processing, Information Retrieval, Machine Learning.

Supervisor: Prof. Uma Shanker TIWARY.

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

• Machine Learning:

Boosting, Deep Learning, Genetic Algorithms, Clustering, Pattern Recognition, etc.

• Computer Vision:

Image Analysis, Image Segmentation.

• Medical Imaging:

Digital Pathology problems of prominent nucleoli detection, gland segmentation, cancer assessment, mutltiplexed fluorescent immuno-phenotype quantification, in histopathological images.

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Programming Languages Software Packages Libraries Explored C, C++, Python, R, Java.
MATLAB, IATEX, gnuplot, ImageJ, Oracle, iMovie, QuPath.
OpenCV, Caffe, TensorFlow, Keras, PyTorch, VTK, scipy, Pysim-

plegui, Matplotlib, Pandas, Seaborn, Boost C++ library.

RELEVANT COURSEWORK

Data and File Structures Database Management Systems Image Processing Information Retrieval Design And Analysis of Algorithms Advanced Modelling and Simulation Distributed Systems Uncertainty Modelling in AI Operating System Computer Networks Soft Computing

WORK EXPERIENCE

Bioinformatics Institute (BII), Singapore.

April 2022 - .

Senior Post-doctoral Research Fellow at the Computer Vision and Pattern Discovery (CVPD) group of BII, Singapore.

Bioinformatics Institute (BII), Singapore.

May 2021 - March 2022.

Post-doctoral Research Fellow at the Computer Vision and Pattern Discovery (CVPD) group of BII, Singapore.

Institute of Molecular and Cell Biology (IMCB), Singapore.

May 2018 - April 2021.

Research Fellow (Post-doctoral) at the Computational & Molecular Pathology Lab (CMPL) of IMCB, Singapore.

National University of Singapore, Singapore

August 2015 - December 2015.

Part Time Teaching Assistant at Department of Computer Science,

- Tutor for
 - CS3244 Machine Learning and
 - CS6205 Advanced Modelling and Simulation modules

at Department of Computer Science, National University of Singapore.

• Lecturers: Prof. Chew Lim TAN and Dr. Hwee Kuan LEE.

University of Alberta, Canada

May 2011 - July 2011.

Research Assistant in "Optimization of CO_2 Injectivity in Geological Carbon Storage" project with Prof. J. Fraser Forbes and Prof. Vinay Prasad.

- Implemented a model of oil reservoirs using MATLAB and studied the relation between well location and migration of CO_2 in depleted or near-depleted oil Reservoirs.
- Optimized the amount of Carbon Dioxide injected into the reservoir within the constraints of Parameters like Bottom Hole Pressure, Permeability and Porosity of rocks.
- Implemented the optimisation using both constrained non-linear programming and genetic algorithm based solvers in MATLAB.

National University of Singapore, Singapore January 2013 - December 2017 Supervisors: Dr. Hwee Kuan LEE and Prof. Wing-Kin SUNG, Ken.

Weblink: PDF@NUS Scholarbank

- Developed an automated image based prominent nucleoli detection system for histopathological images.
- Developed a machine learning and image processing based automated system for gland segmentation in prostate histopathological images.
- Developed an automated image based grading system using nuclear patterns for renal histopathological images.

The above projects were implemented using C++, OpenCV, and Python.

Indian Institute of Information Technology-Allahabad, India January 2012 - July 2012 Supervisor: Prof. Uma Shanker TIWARY

- Development of software using CMUSPhinx library, C++ and Java to transcribe a large amount of audio data into text format and facilitate search using audio queries.
- Use of multiple text document summarization based approach by incorporating human knowledge represented via fuzzy logic-based word-mesh and sentence-mesh.

PUBLICATIONS

Journal Publications

- 1. Mustafa Umit Oner*, Mei Ying Ng*, Danilo Medina Giron, Cecilia Ee Chen Xi, Louis Ang Yuan Xiang, Malay Singh, Weimiao Yu, Wing-Kin Sung, Chin Fong Wong, and Hwee Kuan Lee. An AI-assisted Tool For Efficient Prostate Cancer Diagnosis in Low-grade and Low-volume Cases. Patterns 3 (12), 100642 (2022). DOI: PDF. Dataset and Code(GitHub). *Equal contribution.
- 2. Bhav Harshad Parikh*, Zengping Liu*, Paul Blakeley, Qianyu Lin, Malay Singh, Jun Yi Ong, Kim Han Ho, Joel Weijia Lai, Hanumakumar Bogireddi, Kim Chi Tran, Jason Y. C. Lim, Kun Xue, Abdurrahmaan Al-Mubaarak, Binxia Yang, Sowmiya R, Kakkad Regha, Daniel Soo Lin Wong, Queenie Shu Woon Tan, Zhongxing Zhang, Anand D. Jeyasekharan, Veluchamy Amutha Barathi, Weimiao Yu, Kang Hao Cheong, Timothy A. Blenkinsop, Walter Hunziker, Gopal Lingam, Xian Jun Loh, and Xinyi Su. A bio-functional polymer that prevents retinal scarring through modulation of NRF2 signalling pathway. Nature Communications 13, 2796 (2022). *Equal contribution. PDF.
- 3. Daniel Aitor Holdbrook*, **Malay Singh***, Yukti Choudhury, Emarene Mationg Kalaw, Valerie Koh, Hui Shan Tan, Ravindran Kanesvaran, Puay Hoon Tan, John Yuen Shyi Peng, Min-Han Tan, and Hwee Kuan Lee. **Automated Renal Cancer Grading Using Nuclear Pleomorphic Patterns**. JCO Clinical Cancer Informatics 2018:2, 1-12. *Equal contribution. PDF.
- 4. Oleg V. Grinchuk, Surya Pavan Yenamandra, Ramakrishnan Iyer, **Malay Singh**, Hwee Kuan Lee, Igor V. Kurochkin, Kiat Hon Lim, Pierce K. H. Chow, and Vladimir A. Kuznetsov. **Tumor-adjacent tissue co-expression profile analysis reveals pro-oncogenic gene signature for prognosis of resectable hepatocellular carcinoma**. Molecular Oncology 12(1):89-113, 2018. PDF.
- 5. Malay Singh, Emarene Mationg Kalaw, Danilo Medina Giron, Kian-Tai Chong, Chew Lim Tan, and Hwee Kuan Lee. Gland Segmentation in Prostate Histopathological Images. Journal of Medical Imaging: 4(2), 027501, 2017. PDF.

 Choon Kong Yap, Emarene M. Kalaw, Malay Singh, Kian-Tai Chong, Danilo M. Giron, Chao-Hui Huang, Li Cheng, Yan Nei Law, and Hwee Kuan Lee. Automated Image Based Prominent Nucleoli Detection. Journal of Pathology Informatics 6.1. 2015: 39. PDF.

Conference Posters

- 1. Kok Haur ONG, Laurent Gole, Longjie LI, Xinmi HUO, Kah Weng LAU, David M. YOUNG, Susan Swee Shan HUE, Char Loo TAN, Gabriel Pik Liang MARINI, Hao HAN, Malay Singh, Haoda LU, Soo Yong TAN*, Weimiao YU*. Digital pathology annotation & image quality assessment platform for developing and training various AI cancer models and realizing the intelligent clinical assessment. Poster presentation at HPCAsia2023: International Conference on High Performance Computing in Asia Pacific Region (HPCAsia2023). 27 Feb -2 March 2023. HPCAsia2023. *Corresponding Authors.
- 2. Nicholas Cheng, Eddy W. P. Tan, Shuang Leng, Lohendran Baskaran, Lynette Teo, Min Sen Yew, Malay Singh, Weimin Huang, Mark Yan-Yee Chan, Kee Yuan Ngiam, Roger Vaughan, Terrance Chua, Swee Yaw Tan, Hwee Kuan Lee, Liang Zhong. Machine Learning Accurately Quantifies Epicardial Adipose Tissue from non-contrast CT images in Coronary Artery Disease. Poster presentation at ESC Asia 2022 with APSC & AFC Conference by European Society of Cardiology. Singapore. December 2022. ESC2022.
- 3. Malay Singh, Laurent Gole, Kok Haur Ong, Longjie Li, Xinmi Huo, Hao Han, Kah Weng Lau, Li Mei Gan, Char Loo Tan, David M Young, Hwee Kuan Lee, Susan Swee Shan Hue, Weimiao Yu, and Soo Yong Tan. Highly multiplexed immuno-fluorescence images data analysis for prostate cancer. Poster at "Frontiers in Cancer Science 2021". FCS2021.
- 4. Malay Singh, Laurent Gole, Kok Haur Ong, Hao Han, David M Young, Susan Swee Shan Hue, Soo Yong Tan, and Weimiao Yu. Highly multiplexed immuno-fluorescence images data analysis for prostate cancer. Poster at "Frontiers in Cancer Science 2020". FCS2020.
- 5. Brandon Ryan Hong, Malay Singh, Jane Vin Chan, Matan Thangavelu, Giridharan Periyasamy, Hwee Kuan Lee, and Judice L. Y. Koh. Predicting Drug Response in 3D Tumor Spheroids using Convolutional Neural Networks. Poster at "EMBL Symposium: Seeing is Believing Imaging the Process of Life". EMBL Heidelberg, Germany. October 2017.

Conference Articles

- Malay Singh, Zeng Zeng, Emarene Mationg Kalaw, Danilo Medina Giron, Kian-Tai Chong, and Hwee Kuan Lee. A Study of Nuclei Classification Methods in Histopathological Images. International Conference on Innovation in Medicine and Healthcare (KES-InMed-17). Springer, 2017. PDF.
- Malay Singh, Uma Shanker Tiwary, and Tanveer J. Siddiqui. A Speech Retrieval System based on Fuzzy logic and Knowledge-base filtering. In Proceedings of International Conference on Multimedia, Signal Processing and Communication Technologies (IMPACT), 2013, pp. 46-50. IEEE, 2013. PDF.
- 3. Anupam Srivastava, Divij Vaidya, Malay Singh, Pranjal Singh, and Uma Shanker Tiwary. A Cognitive Interactive Framework for Multi-Document Summarizer. Advances in Intelligent Systems and Computing, 1, Volume 179, Proceedings of the Third International Conference on Intelligent Human Computer Interaction (IHCI 2011), Prague, Czech Republic, August, 2011, Part 5, Pages 257-268. PDF.

Preprints

1. Balakrishnan Chakrapani Narmada, Atefeh Khakpoor, Niranjan Shirgaonkar, Sriram Narayanan, Pauline Poh Kim Aw, **Malay Singh**, Kok Haur Ong, Collins Oduor Owino, Jane Wei Ting

Ng, Hui Chuing Yew, Nu Soibah Binte Mohamed Nasir, Veonice Bijin Au, Reina Sng, Nivashini Kaliaperumal, Htet Htet Toe Wai Khine, Hui Xin Ng, Su Li Chia, Cindy Xin Yi Seah, Myra HJ Alnawaz, Chris Lee Yoon Wai, Amy Yuh Ling Tay, Weimiao Yu, John Edward Connolly, Giridharan Periyasamy, Seng Gee Lim, and Ramanuj Dasgupta. Single cell profiling of functionally cured Chronic Hepatitis B patients reveals the emergence of activated innate and an altered adaptive immune response in the intra-hepatic environment. bioRxiv 2022.04.26.489625. Under Review, 2023. PDF.

 Malay Singh, Emarene Mationg Kalaw, Wang Jie, Mundher Al-Shabi, Chin Fong Wong, Danilo Medina Giron, Kian-Tai Chong, Maxine Tan, Zeng Zeng, and Hwee Kuan Lee. Cribriform pattern detection in prostate histopathological images using deep learning models. arXiv pre-print, 1910.04030. PDF.

DATE: February 4, 2023